Preliminary Inventory to the M. H. De Young Memorial Museum Collection, 1914-1919
Hoover Institution Archives
M. H. De Young Memorial Museum collection,
1914-1919
63014
M. H. De Young Memorial Museum
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize envelope, 1 framed newspaper sheet (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs, maps, proclamations, and printed matter, relating to World War I. Includes United States Shipping Board posters, photographs of the American Expeditionary Forces in France, battle maps, statistical summaries concerning the American Expeditionary Forces, German proclamations in France and Belgium, and a letter from General John J. Pershing to Congressman Julius Kahn. Collected by the M. H. De Young Memorial Museum.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Pershing, John Joseph, 1860-1948.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces--Pictorial works.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Aerial operations.; World War, 1914-1918--Pictorial works.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Armed Forces.; Kahn, Julius.; M. H. De Young Memorial Museum (San Francisco); United States. Shipping Board.
Container List
- German pamphlet, To the American Soldier of German Descent (in English), 44 956. (Box 1-3.)
- German pamphlet, Furchte Dich Nicht, 45 631.
- German leaflet, "An Heer Und Heimat" (To Army and Home), 1918 September 2, 45 632.
- German loan poster, with insets of agricultural implements, horse and cow on outer border, 45 634.
- Photo of inscription written by Queen Marie of Romania to American soldiers in address book at Aix-les- Bains, 1919 April, 45 644.
- Newspaper issue, La Libre Belgique, no. 78, 1916 June, 45 646.
- News sheet, 1919 January 15 (in French and Flemish), 45 647.
- Swiss ration cards: 2 milk cards, 1 food fat card, and 1 bread card, 45 648.
- French map of Paris and environs: air raid over Paris, 1918 March 11-12, 45 651.
- French map of Paris and environs: air raid over Paris, 1918 May 22-23, 45 652.
- French map of Paris and environs: air raid over Paris, 1918 June 27-28, 45 653.
- French map of Paris and environs: air raid over Paris, 1918 June 15-16, 45 654.
- French map of Paris and environs: air raid over Paris, 1918 June 2, 45 655.
- French map of Paris and environs: air raid over Paris, 1918 July 18-19, 45 656.
- French map of Paris and environs: air raid over Paris, 1918 September 15-16, 45 657.
- Map of French terrain, "Order of Battle on Western Front, November 11, 1918, 11:00 A.M.," Base Printing Plant, 29th Engineers, U.S.A., 1919, 45 658.
- Battle map, "Extract of Metz-Commercy, May 21, 1918," St. Mihiel Offensive, 45 659.
- Map, "The Meuse-Argonne Offensive," France, Base Printing Plant, 29th Engineers, U.S.A., 1918, 45 660.
- Map, "Distribution of U.S. Forces, August 9, 1918, France", 45 661.
- Map, "Second Battle of the Marne" (disposition of U.S. forces), 45 662.
- Map, "Lateral Railroads, 1918," Map Room, G-3, G.H.Q., 1919 April 8, 45 663.
- American battle map, "Extract of Mezieres-Verdun-Metz Longwy, May 24, 1919," 29th Engineers, U.S.A., 45 664.
- Battle "Ostend, Belgium," Geographical Section, General Staff, no. 2364, British War Office, 1911, 45 665.
- Map, "The Western Theater of the European War" by Prof. B. Barrecchia, 1919, showing route taken by Congressman Julius Kahn and party, 45 666.
- Map, German, "Rhineland and Westphalia", 45 667.
- Map, German, sightseeing, "Relief Panorama of the Rhine", 45 668.
- Map, "The St. Mihiel Salient, September 12-15,1918," Base Printing Plant, 29th Engineers, U.S.A., 1919, 45 669.
- Chart showing in color the shoulder patches of the units of the American Expeditionary Forces, Base Printing Plant, 29th Engineers, U.S.A., 1918, 45 670.
- Ten receipts for merchandise from Cologne, Germany, 1918 April 3, 45 671.
- Three American military transit passes issued to Congressman Julius Kahn, dated 1919 April 2, Headquarters, 3rd Army, Coblenz, Germany, 45 677.
- American pass issued to Congressman Julius Kahn, 1919 April 2, Headquarters, 3rd Army, 45 678.
- Three military transit passes issued to Dr. Morris Herzstein, 1919 April 2, Headquarters, 3rd Army, Coblenz, Germany, 45 679.
- Passenger identification card issued to Morris Merzstein, U.S. Customs, New York City, 1919 March 9, 45 680.
- Tabulation of air raids over Paris in 1918. Typescript (in English), 45 681.
- Travel order issued to Dr. Morris Merzstein to board the SS Leviathan, 1919 May 13, Brest, France, 45 683.
- Description of Camp Pontenazen, France, embarkation point for U.S. soldiers returning to America. Typescript, 45 684.
- Invitation extended to Congressman Julius Kahn by the 322nd Field Signal Battalion, 1919 March 24, signed by all Californians in the battalion. Typescript, 45 685.
- Description of Camp St. Sulpice, France. Typescript, 45 682.
- Letter to Congressman Julius Kahn from Chief of Staff, 80th Division, 1919 March 27; and General Order no. 2, Headquarters, 80th Division, 1919 March 26. Typescript, 45 686.
- Newspaper issue, The Amroc News, Coblenz, Germany, 1919 June 28, published by Americans in occupied Germany. (this issue announces the signing of the Peace Treaty), 45 802.
- Battle map of Verdun: operation of the 181st and 182nd Brigades, U.S.A., on 1918 August 12, 45 907.
- Eight framed photos of U.S. carrier pigeons used in the war, 45 912.
- Map, "Condition of Peace of All Allied and Associates Powers: Complete and Revised Reproduction of the Official Text, 1919," published by H. R. Englemann, Berlin, Germany, 45 975.
- Volume, Summary Statistics of the American Expeditionary Forces, 45 977.
- Booklet, Return of Troops to the U.S. From November 11, 1918 to May 31, 1919: Report for Month of May, 45 978.
- Booklet, Official Souvenir Program of the Victory Parades, by authority of the War Department, 1st Division, U.S.A., 46 237.
- Document in portfolio, "History of the Signing of the Treaty of Peace, As Recorded by Original Telegrams Filed at the U.S. Signal Corps Telegraph Office, Palace of Versailles, 1919 June 28", 46 238.
- Two admission tickets to reviewing stand for review of the last division, U.S.A., 1919 September 17, Washington, D.C., 46 240.
- Portfolio of 16 war photographs, U.S. Army Signal Corps, 46 242.
- Proclamation demanding the reporting to German authorities of all English military refugees, posted in Mons, France, 1914 November 16 (in French), 46 243.
- Proclamation posted in Brussels, Belgium, 1914 August 20, by Burgomaster Adolphe Max, 46 244.
- Proclamation posted in Brusssels, Belgium, 1914 September 16, by the burgomaster, protesting the removal of Belgian flags (in French and Flemish), 46 245.
- Proclamation posted in the Ardennes, 1914 August 25, by Captain Schultzee, German Commander (in French), 46 246.
- Proclamation posted at Cugnon, 1914 October, by Burgomaster Delmue (in French), 46 247.
- Proclamation posted in Brussels, Belgium, 1916 July 12, by Lt. General Hurt, German Governor of Brussels and Brabant (in German, French and Flemish), 46 248.
- Poster announcing the closing of all stores as mute manifestation of the Belgian National Fete Day, year? July 21, 46 249.
- Poster posted in Louvain, Belgium, 1914 October 24, by the provisional burgomaster, protesting the German taking of hostages, 46 250.
- Proclamation posted in Ghent, Belgium, 1915 June 10, by Lt. General von Westarp (in German, French and Flemish), 46 251.
- Proclamation posted in Brussels, 1914 September 25, by Baron von der Goltz, Governor General of Belgium (in German, French and Flemish), 46 252.
- Proclamation posted in the Ardennes, 1914 August 22, by Major Scheunemann, German Army (in French), 46 253.
- Proclamation posted in Antwerp, 1914 October 9, by Von Beseler, Commander in Chief of the German Armies, 46 254.
- Proclamation posted in Louvain, 1914 October 1, by the German Governor General of Brussels (in German, French and Flemish), 46 255.
- Proclamation posted in the Ardennes, 1914 August 29, by Becker, Commander in Chief (in French), 46 256.
- Proclamation by German General von Luttewitz announcing the arrest of the Belgian mayor, 1914 September 26 (in German and French), 46 257.
- Proclamation posted in the Ardennes, 1914 August 21, by the burgomaster on German order, 46 258.
- Proclamation posted in the Ardennes, 1914 August 30, by the burgomaster, 46 259.
- Proclamation posted in St. Trond, 1914 September 6, by Lt. Colonel Bleyhoffer (in German, French and Flemish), 46 260.
- German war news poster posted in Brussels, 1914 September 6, by the German Military Government (in German, French and Flemish), 46 261.
- German proclamation posted in Belgium, 1914 (in German), 46 262.
- German war news poster posted in Belgium, 1914 September 29 (in French, German and Flemish), 46 263.
- German war news poster posted in Belgium (in French, German and Flemish), 46 264.
- Proclamation posted in Brussels, 1915 October 12, announcing the condemnation to death of Nurse Cavell, 46 265.
- Illustrated Belgian poster, Royal Institution of Messines, near Ypres, for the daughters of Belgian officers and soldiers, killed and wounded, 46 266.
- The Marshall Foch Victory-Marmony Banner, 46 267.
- Five booklets, Scraps of Paper, on German proclamations in Belgium and France, with foreword by Ian Malcolm, M.P., London, 1916, 46 506.
- Newspaper issue, La Libre Belgique, no. 126, 1917 August, 46 508.
- Letter from General John J. Pershing to Congressman Julius Kahn, 1919 November 5, re universal military training, 46 535.
- Booklet, Personnel Statistics Report: Strength of Army as of October 1, 1919, copy no. 24, 46 540.
- Booklet, Weekly Statistical Report No. 113, October 25, 1919, published by the Statistics Branch, General Staff, War Department, copy no. 39, 46 541.
- Five French bread ration cards, 1919 January, February, March, April and May, 47 490.
- German war map, Wald von Montfaucon district, 48 138.
- French color print, souvenir of Camp Courtine, France, 48 353.
- Fragment of the gas bag from the airplane that exploded over Hull, England, on the way to America, 1921 August (marked R28, Bag No. 5, Body Gore No. 40), 48 975.
- Map of Serbia, 49 569.
- Piece of fuselage covering from the NC3, U.S. Navy sea plane that left Newfoundland, 1919 May, and reached the Azores, 45 649.
- Program for the Aviators Ball, Hotel Ritz Carlton, New York City, 1919 April 26, Not numbered.
- Sheet music, "When Madelon" or "Quand Madelon," published by L. Bousquet, Paris, 1036R.
- "Certificate of Enrollment in the U.S. Shipyard Volunteers of the Public Service Reserve," of Henry Lux, 858 R.
- 858 R. Certificate pertaining to Henry Lux (in German)
- Thirteen war posters issued by the United States Shipping Board Emergency Fleet Corporation, Publications Section, Philadelphia, Not numbered.